地          球          脉          动
这里是地球上最后的边缘地带
This is our planet's final frontier,
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
一个只有最勇敢者 才敢涉足的地底世界
an inner world where only the most adventurous dare to go.
洞  穴  迷  宫
我们脚下有着绵延不绝的洞窟和隧道
Beneath our feet are countless miles of cave shafts and passages.
墨西哥境内的燕子洞
The Cave of Swallows in Mexico,
深达400多米
400 metres to the bottom,
足以吞没整座帝国大厦
deep enough to engulf the Empire State Building.
这是世界上最大的深洞
This is the biggest cave shaft in the world.
然而人类直到登月前两年 才第一次进入这个深渊
Yet these depths were first explored only two years before man landed on the moon.
今天 洞穴仍是地球上 人类最少涉足的地方
Today caves remain the least explored places on Earth.
但是 人类绝非 这个阴暗潮湿地界的第一位到访者
However, human beings are seldom the first to reach these black, damp places.
这里住着一些地球上最奇异 和最鲜为人知的动物
Here, live some of the strangest and least-known animals on the planet.
这“满天星斗”其实是 几千只小动物发出的荧光
This galaxy of little lights is created by thousands of living creatures.
住在洞穴里的动物都必须 适应彻底黑暗的环境
Any animal that lives in a cave has to cope with complete blackness,
但是在新西兰  有些动物却能利用黑暗的条件
but in New Zealand some have turned this darkness to their advantage.
一根坚韧的丝从天顶上垂下
A silicon strand is lowered from the ceiling,
边上还有好几百根
alongside hundreds of others.
虽然这些丝看起来很漂亮
Beautiful though these threads are,
它们却是阴险的陷阱
they have a sinister purpose.
这是一种洞穴萤火虫
This is a cave glow worm.
它利用一根根的丝来诱捕猎物
To trap its prey it goes fishing with a line of silk.
丝产生自萤火虫口中的腺体
The silk comes from glands in the glow worm's mouth
上面缀着一串粘液滴
and is loaded with droplets of mucus.
每条萤火虫都会吐很多根这样的丝
Each glow worm produces dozens of these threads.
当一排丝架设完毕后
Once its lines are set,
萤火虫便用粘液将自己悬吊起来
the glow worm hangs from a mucus hammock
然后像一位耐心的钓鱼者似的 等待猎物上钩
and waits, like a patient angler.
不过 萤火虫并不会听天由命
But the glow worm doesn't leave everything to chance.
这些诡异的蓝光是一种化学反应的结果
That ghostly blue light is the result of a chemical reaction
由尾部的一个特殊腔囊产生
taking place inside a special capsule in its tail.
这些从尾部发散出来的荧光
The light literally shines out of its backside.
正是用来吸引猎物的诱饵
It's a lure for attracting prey.
昆虫总是禁不住光源的诱惑
Insects seem irresistibly drawn towards the source
结果就被这些粘乎乎的丝拿住了
and then get trapped by the sticky lines.
一旦被粘住
Once stuck,
根本没有脱逃的机会
there is no escape.
现在 它只需收起丝线
Now it's just a matter of reeling in the line
然后慢慢吃掉尚且活着的猎物
and slowly consuming the catch - alive.
通过诱捕洞穴内羽化的昆虫
By ensnaring the insects that hatch in this cave,
这些萤火虫成功地解决了 终生穴居动物面临的最大难题
these glow worms have solved the biggest challenge that permanent cave dwellers face -
即找到长期而可靠的食物资源
finding a regular and reliable source of food.
这些地底世界之所以会存在  都是因为一种岩石
One kind of rock makes this whole underground world possible -
石灰岩
limestone.
世界上大部分洞穴内都存在石灰岩
Most of the world's caves are found within it
它覆盖了地球表面将近10%的面积
and it covers nearly 10 percent of the earth's surface.
石灰岩由海螺和 珊瑚中的矿物沉积后形成
Limestone is composed of minerals derived from marine shells and corals,
所以 尽管美国境内的这座石壁 如今矗立在海平面以上几百米高的地方
so although this rocky escarpment in the United States is now hundreds of metres above sea level
它实际上却是在水下形成的
it was actually formed under water.
越南下龙湾的石林
The limestone towers of Vietnam's Ha Long Bay
能说明石灰岩与海洋的关系
are a reminder of this link with the sea.
起初 这整个地方都是 一整块坚固的石灰岩床
Originally, this whole area would have been one solid block of limestone,
珊瑚礁的基座
the base of a coral reef.
在婆罗洲 雨水已将石灰岩 雕凿成无比尖削的石塔
In Borneo, rain has sculptured the limestone into extremely sharp-sided pinnacles.
不过在地下 雨水的溶解作用 还能产生其它更壮观的效果
But the dissolving power of rainwater has other, much more dramatic effects underground.
流经石灰岩的河川 到最后似乎总是无影无踪
Rivers that flow over limestone often seem to completely disappear.
当水流遇到更坚硬的石灰岩床时
When the water reaches the more resistant bed of limestone
就会改变路线
its course is altered.
一旦进入地下
Once underground,
水便有了一股新的、更强的侵蚀力
the water takes on a new, more erosive power.
在地面上流淌时
During its journey from the surface
水从土壤中吸收了二氧化碳
the water absorbed carbon dioxide from the soil
成为弱酸性
making it mildly acidic.
石灰岩经过几百万年的酸蚀作用
And over millions of years this acid eats away the limestone
形成了迷宫般的溶洞和通道
creating a maze of caverns and passages
有的甚至深达数英里
that sometimes go on for miles.
这是世界上最大的地下河通道
This is the biggest underground river passage in the world,
大到可以通过一架大型喷气式客机
so big a jumbo jet could fly through it.
它就是婆罗洲的鹿洞
It's Deer Cave, in Borneo.
鹿洞的容量很大
The sheer size of Deer Cave
使得大批动物到此聚集
allows some animals to gather there in huge numbers.
这里住着数量惊人的300万只犬吻蝠
A staggering 3 million wrinkle-lipped bats live here.
这些蝙蝠倒挂在洞壁和天顶上
The bats roost high on the walls and ceilings
它们在此完全不受外界因素的干扰
where they're well protected from the outside elements
还能躲开天敌
and safe from predators.
它们高悬在洞穴上方时
And while they're up here
会产生一种非常重要的东西
the bats produce something very important.
这堆100多米高的东西 全都是蝙蝠的排泄物
This hundred metre high mound is made entirely of bat droppings -
粪便
guano.
地面上爬满了密密麻麻的蟑螂
Its surface is covered by a thick carpet of cockroaches,
它们的数量无以为计
hundreds of thousands of them.
洞穴是地球上少数几种 不直接依赖阳光的生态环境之一
Caves are one of the few habitats on Earth not directly powered by sunlight.
在缺少植物的情况下 这里的食物链 完全依赖供应不断的蝙蝠粪便
In the absence of plants this food chain is based on a continuous supply of bat droppings.
蟑螂的食物就是粪便
The cockroaches feed on the guano
以及任何掉进里面的东西
and anything that falls into it.
粪便也能养活其它种类的蟑螂
The droppings also support other types of cockroaches
它们一天大部分时间都呆在洞壁上
which spend part of their day resting on cave walls.
这些蟑螂也接连成为了 洞穴大蚰蜒的美餐
These in turn become food for giant cave centipedes,
有的蚰蜒能长到20厘米长
some more than 20 centimetres long.
奇怪的是 这里甚至还有螃蟹
Bizarrely, there are crabs here, too,
它们从粪便中过滤营养物质
sifting through the droppings for nutrients.
所有这些动物都在洞穴内度过一生
All these animals spend their entire lives within the cave.
它们完全依赖的食物消化残渣 都是来自于外界
They're totally dependant on the digested remains of food that's brought here from outside.
每天傍晚 只是前后2小时内
Each evening in just two hours
300万只蝙蝠一起离开安全的洞穴
three million bats leave the safety of the cave
在森林外围捕食昆虫
to hunt for insects in the forest outside.
但并非所有的蝙蝠都能返回
But not all will return.
蝙蝠离开山洞后
As they leave the cave
即在空中组成一个面包圈一样的队列
the stream of bats form a doughnut-shaped ring.
旋绕的蝙蝠群似乎已将 棕腹隼雕弄得晕头转向
The wheeling bats seem to confuse a rufus-bellied eagle,
但它们仍须躲过 其它更专业的猛禽的攻击
but they must still survive the attacks of other, more specialised, birds of prey.
游隼和蝠鹞是鸟类中的喷气式战斗机
Peregrine falcons and bat hawks are the jetfighters of the bird world.
天黑后 再高超的捕猎本领 也将无用武之地
Good hunting will end as the light fades
于是蝠鹞一边飞一边吞下猎物
so the bat hawks bolt their catches on the wing
然后径直返回继续捕猎
and fly straight back for more.
任何一只脱离群体的蝙蝠
Any bat separated from the group
立刻成为显眼的目标 很快便遭了殃
becomes a clear and obvious target and is asking for trouble.
然而 每天傍晚的攻击只会 对蝙蝠数量产生很小的影响
Yet the nightly onslaught has little impact on bat numbers -
到了早上 大多数蝙蝠 仍会安然无恙地回到洞中
by the morning the vast majority will be back in the safety of the cave.
蝙蝠并非婆罗洲洞窟中的唯一常客
Bats are not the only commuters in these Bornean caves.
这里也有“做日班”的居民
There's a day shift as well.
完成白天的狩猎工作后
Returning from hunting in the sunlight
这些住客利用它们响亮的叫声 在漆黑一片的洞穴通道内辨别方向
these commuters rely on their loud clicks to find their way through the cave passages in total darkness.
它们就是洞金丝燕
They're cave swiftlets.
和蝙蝠一样  它们也利用回声定位来导航
Like bats they use echolocation to navigate.
我们必须有光才能看清前方的路
We need lights to see what's going on,
但是金丝燕却能在黑暗中 准确无误地到达自己的筑巢点
but in the pitch black the swiftlets manage unerringly to locate their individual nesting sites,
而它们的巢窝相隔不过几厘米远
which are only a few centimetres across.
我们至今仍未能完全了解 这种了不起的本领
It's a remarkable skill and one we still do not fully understand.
这些鸟之所以特别还有另外一个原因
These birds are unusual for another reason.
它们小巧的杯状燕窝完全由唾液丝筑建
Their little cup-like nests are made entirely from threads of saliva.
每个燕窝得花上30多天才能完工
It takes more than 30 days to complete one.
燕窝是非常珍贵的东西
The nests are very precious objects,
不仅只是针对这些鸟而言
and not only for the birds.
500年来 人们一直采集洞金丝燕的燕窝
For 500 years people have been harvesting the nests of cave swiftlets.
这是一项非常危险的工作
It's a very risky business.
事实上没有任何安全措施
with virtually no safety equipment
采集者利用树藤编成的梯子爬到洞穴的最高处
and using ladders made from forest vines the gatherers climb into the highest reaches of the cave
通常高出地面60多米
often more than 60 metres from the floor.
这项工作看起来极度危险
The work may be hazardous in the extreme,
但却能得到丰厚的回报
but the rewards are great.
洞金丝燕的纯白燕窝
The pure white nests of cave swiftlets
是燕窝羹的主要成分
are the main ingredient of birds' nest soup
每克燕窝的价值堪比白银
and gram for gram are worth as much as silver.
燕窝被摘去后  金丝燕很快又会再吐一个
As soon as its nest is removed a bird will immediately build another.
所以 只要这种利润可观的 采摘行为得到适当控制
So, as long as this valuable harvest is properly controlled,
燕群仍旧可以长盛不衰
the colonies will continue to flourish.
婆罗洲的这些洞窟是世界上最大的洞穴
These Bornean caves are among the biggest in the world
它们仍在不断扩大
and they're still getting bigger
因为每年雨水都会侵蚀掉少许石灰岩
as each year rainwater eats away a little more limestone.
可是洞里的水不光只是侵蚀
But water in caves doesn't only erode.
它们还能造景
It also builds.
这些水中含有溶解的碳酸钙
This water is loaded with dissolved limestone
当它与洞内空气接触时
and when it meets the air in the cave
其中的一些就会沉淀为一种矿物
some of that is deposited as a mineral -
方解石
calcite.
随着它的积累
As it builds up
方解石形成了悬在洞顶上的装饰物
so the calcite forms decorations that hang from the ceiling -
钟乳石
stalactites.
每滴水珠只会留下极少量的方解石微粒
Each drop leaves behind only a miniscule amount of calcite,
但随着时间的推移  它们变成了最引人入胜的景观
but over time the process can produce some spectacular results.
若是水从洞顶滴落的速度较快
If the water seeps though the ceiling quickly,
方解石就会在洞穴地面上沉积
then the calcite is deposited on the floor of the cave
最后形成石笋
and that creates stalagmites.
水流和气流的变化
Variations in water flow and the air currents
造就了千姿百态的溶洞地形  但它们的形成过程都是一样的
produce an infinite variety of forms, but all are created by the same process -
都是由水溶碳酸钙缓慢沉淀而来
the slow deposition of dissolved limestone.
钟乳石与石笋相遇后
And when stalactite meets stalagmite
便形成了石柱
a column is born.
北美洲卡尔斯巴德溶洞中的这些构造
Structures like these in North America's Carlsbad Cavern
经历了数千年的形成过程
can take many thousands of years to develop.
但有时洞穴内的这些活动会完全停止
But sometimes the formations in a cave stop growing altogether.
墨西哥的这些水洞 几千年来几乎保持不变
These flooded caves in Mexico have remained virtually unchanged for thousands of years.
自从上一个冰川期以来  它们便已和外界隔绝
Since the last Ice Age they've become cut off from the outside world.
然而它们对地面上的生物 却有着极其深远的影响
Yet their impact on life on the surface has been huge.
500年前 它们维系着 一个世界上最伟大的文明
500 years ago they supported one of the world's great civilisations
玛雅
the Maya.
墨西哥的尤卡坦半岛 没有河流、湖泊和小溪
Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula has no rivers, lakes or streams
因此玛雅文化完全依赖于沼穴 ——地下水洞的入口
so the Maya relied on the cenotes - the flooded entrances to the water-filled caves.
这些水潭是整个地区 唯一的露天淡水资源
These flooded shafts are the region's only source of open fresh water.
沼穴于是成了巨大的淡水井
The cenotes are, in effect, gigantic fresh water wells.
这里远离给予生命的阳光
Away from the life-giving rays of sunshine
似乎不太可能会有植物
one might not expect to find plants.
但是在黑暗的洞穴通道内
But in the darkness of the cave tunnels
大型热带树木的根系 却已穿透石灰岩裂缝
roots of giant tropical trees have pushed their way through cracks in the limestone
伸入到水洞之中
to reach the flooded caverns.
如果没有这些水
Without this water
尤卡坦半岛的森林不可能长得如此茂盛
the Yucatan's forest could not grow so luxuriantly.
玛雅人固然知道 它们的生活离不开这些水
The Maya knew that their lives depended on this water,
但只有借助现代科技
but it's only with the help of today's technology
我们才能完全了解 这些地下水道的重要性及其规模
that we've come to appreciate the full significance and scale of these flooded passageways.
人们迄今为止已绘制了350英里的 尤卡坦半岛地下水系图
So far, more than 350 miles of underwater galleries in the Yucatan have been mapped,
但仍旧无人知晓 这个地下水世界究竟有多大
but still nobody yet knows the true extend of this subterranean waterworld.
以及它形成的原因
And with good reason.
地下水洞是出了名的危险
Underwater caving is notoriously dangerous.
最近的出口可能远在 几百米之外或者更远的地方
When the nearest exit may be hundreds of metres or more away,
在这里 耗尽氧气将是致命的
running out of air down here would be fatal.
为了避免迷路
To avoid getting lost
潜水员必须随身携带一捆轴线
divers carry with them a spool of string.
这成了它们的救生索
It becomes their lifeline -
绝对如此
literally.
这根线同时也是测量尺
The string also doubles as a measuring tape -
在墨西哥的这个地方 这种科技被用来 测绘世界上最大的地下水洞
a technique that has been used here, in Mexico, to chart the largest underwater cave in the world -
全长达100多英里
all 100 miles of it.
洞穴探险需要不时挤过 一些狭窄的岩石缝隙
Cave exploration often requires you to push yourself through narrow gaps in the rock.
洞穴专家称之为“瓶颈”
Cavers call such places 'squeezes.'
“瓶颈”越是狭窄
The tighter the squeeze,
便越有可能损坏一些重要的生存设备
the greater the chance of damaging some vital life-support system.
在这种情况下  潜水员很容易迷失方向
In these conditions a diver could easily become disorientated
而这将导致送命
and that could be fatal.
地下水洞还会以别的方式戏弄你
The flooded caverns can play tricks on you in other ways.
这看上去像是空气
What seems like air,
不对
isn't.
它只是另一种水
It's just another kind of water.
这里是盐跃层
This is a halocline -
淡水与咸水的交汇处
a meeting of fresh and salt water.
咸水来自海洋 比重较重  来自丛林的淡水在其上方流动
Fresh water from the jungle flows over the heavier salt water from the sea.
咸水层的含氧量很低
The saltwater layer is extremely low in oxygen
对动物而言是极为困难的生境
making it a particularly difficult place for animals to live.
但有些动物却能在此生存
Yet some have managed it,
例如桨足虫——一种最古老的甲壳动物
like the remiped, one of the most ancient of all living crustaceans.
玛雅人知道沼穴的重要性
The Maya understood the importance of the cenotes,
但他们从不知道这些水下通道 其实是地下河的入口
but they could never have known that these flooded passageways were actually the beginning of subterranean rivers,
它们最终都流向大海
all of which eventually flow out to the sea.
咸水与淡水不同 不会溶解石灰岩
Salt water, unlike fresh water, does not erode limestone,
所以大部分海洋洞窟 是在海浪的机械冲击下形成的
so most sea caves are created by the mechanical pounding of the waves.
新西兰坡·骑士岛的 岩礁下布满了海蚀洞
The rocky outcrops of New Zealand's Poor Knight Islands are riddled with sea caves
与婆罗洲的洞窟一样
and just like those in Borneo
它们也成了许多动物的重要庇护所
they have become important shelters for many species.
经过一天开放水域的觅食之后
After a day feeding in the open water
大群雀鲷返回到洞窟中
vast shoals of demoiselle fish return to the caves,
这里是它们躲避天敌的地方
which they use as a refuge from predators.
对于这些鱼来说  洞穴是理想的过夜场所
For these fish the caves are a night time retreat,
但它们并非这里的唯一住客
but they're not the only commuters in here.
这里还有其它 按照不同日程表生活的鱼
There are other fish working to a different schedule.
大眼鲷相当于蝙蝠
The bigeyes are the equivalent of bats.
它们每天晚上出洞觅食
Night feeders leave the cave each evening.
和所有洞穴动物一样
And like all cave commuters
它们在出发阶段最容易遭受攻击
they are most vulnerable at the scheduled time of departure.
当大群蝙蝠密集地通过瓶颈出口时
A bottleneck funnels these exiting bats into dense concentrations
很容易引起其它动物的注意
attracting the attention of others.
蝙蝠能利用回声定位觉察到蛇
The bats can detect the snakes using echolocation,
而蛇则完全处于黑暗之中
but the snakes are literally in the dark -
它们看不见任何东西
they can see nothing.
这种攻击更像是在碰运气
The strikes seem to be largely hit-and-miss,
不过蛇也有自己的秘密武器
but the snakes have a secret weapon.
它们实际上能感觉到 每一只飞过的蝙蝠
They can actually sense each bat flying past.
位于头部的“热眼”能觉察到 飞行中的蝙蝠散发出的热量
Receptors in the snake's head pick up the heat given off by the flying bats,
正如这幅热影像所示
as this thermal image shows.
每一只蝙蝠在蛇“眼”前都是活灵活现
To the snakes the bats are apparently glowing
这也给了它们瞄准目标的机会
and this gives them something to aim at.
这是洞栖动物必须付出的代价
This is the price that these cave commuters must pay
以换取它们白天在陆地上的庇护
for their daytime sanctuary on the ground.
难怪其它洞穴生物 要终生居住在洞穴中
Small wonder then that there are other cave dwellers that stay put.
很多洞穴都和岛屿一样
Many caves are like islands -
与外界及其它洞穴隔绝
cut off from the outside world and from other caves.
这种孤立环境导致进化产生 各种各样奇怪的生物
This isolation has resulted in the evolution of some various strange creatures.
它们都是洞穴专家
They are the cave specialists -
穴居动物——从不出洞并且 永远不见天日的动物
troglodytes, animals that never emerge from the caves or see daylight.
泰国的这些穴居动物
These troglodytes from Thailand
可能是地球上最奇特的动物
are possibly the most specialised creatures on Earth
因为它们只生活在洞穴瀑布中
for they live only in cave waterfalls.
世界上所有的洞穴天使鱼
The entire population of these cave angel fish
可能只存在于两个较小的洞穴中
seems to be restricted to just two small caves.
其它穴居动物也是同样的情况
It's the same story with other troglodytes.
世界上可能只有不到100只 野生洞栖童态河溪螈
There may well be less than a hundred Texas cave salamanders in the wild.
而伯利兹白蟹是另一个 洞穴生态系统中的特有物种
And the Belizean white crab is another creature that is unique to just one cave system.
由于一直生活在黑暗之中
Living in perpetual darkness
它们不仅失去了皮肤色素
they have all not only lost the pigment in their skin,
眼睛也退化了
but also their eyes.
眼睛的退化需要经历数千代的演变
It takes thousands of generations for eyes to be lost,
所以这些物种必定 与世隔绝了相当长的一段时间
so these species must have been isolated for a very long time.
不过这些瞎眼的蝾螈 进化出了其它发达的感觉器官
But the blind salamander has other highly developed sensory organs.
皮肤上的探测器能觉察到 猎物引起的最微小的水流变化
Receptors in their skin detect minute movements in the water made by its prey.
外生的鳃帮助它们 在极度缺氧的水中呼吸
External gills help it to breathe in water that is particularly low in oxygen.
洞穴天使鱼以急流中的细菌为食
The cave angel fish feed on bacteria in the fast flowing water
它们用鳍上的小钩紧紧抓住岩壁
keeping their grip with microscopic hooks on their fins.
食物总是很紧缺
Food is often in short supply
像螃蟹这样的穴居动物
and troglodytes like the crab
必须得吃任何从外边冲进洞内的东西
have to survive on whatever washes into the cave from outside.
童态河溪螈可能 已有几个月没有吃东西了
The salamander might not encounter food for several months,
所以只要眼前有食物出现
so when something does come along
它绝对不会放过
it can't afford to miss it.
这些奇异的洞栖生物能如此成功地生存 的确令人称奇
It's astonishing that these extraordinary cave dwellers manage to survive at all.
可是有一个洞穴的环境过于险恶
But one cave is so inhospitable
不管什么生物似乎都不可能在那里生存
that one would not expect it to contain any life whatsoever.
从墨西哥露兹别墅山洞流出来的水
The water flowing out of the Villa Luz cave in Mexico
竟然被硫酸染成了白色
is actually coloured white with sulphuric acid.
探险家们进入这个危险的山洞时
Explorers entering this dangerous cave
必须戴上防毒面具 并携带通话器
must wear respirators and carry monitors.
有毒气体很快就会达到致命的程度
Poisonous gases rise to fatal levels so quickly
所以即时预警设备是最重要的
that an early warning system is essential.
蝙蝠之所以能生存是因为 它们始终呆在天窗附近
Bats survive by staying close to the skylights,
但是深入洞穴必然极度危险
but venturing deep into the cave is very dangerous indeed.
这些毒气的源头位于地下几英里处
The source of these toxic fumes lies several miles below.
硫化氢气体从地壳内的油气储层中溢出
Hydrogen sulphide gas bubbles up from oil deposits in the earth's crust.
与水中的氧发生化合反应
It mixes with oxygen and the water,
产生了硫酸
and forms sulphuric acid.
鱼类似乎不太可能生活在这种环境中
These are not the sort of conditions in which you would expect to find fish,
然而这些洞栖帆鳍? 看上去却是悠然自得
yet these cave mollies seem to thrive
尽管这里是酸性低含氧量环境
despite the acid and the low levels of oxygen.
事实上 这里的生物数量 远比人们预料的更多
There is, in fact, more life here than anyone would think possible,
不过更大的惊奇莫过于 那些更奇怪的东西
but the biggest surprise is something altogether more bizarre.
这些奇特的钟乳石状的结构  确切地说 叫做“鼻涕石”
These strange stalactite-like formations are known, rather appropriately, as snotites,
其末端滴落的液滴就是硫酸
the drops dripping from the ends are sulphuric acid,
酸性强到足以腐蚀皮肤
strong enough to burn skin.
“鼻涕石”其实是大型菌落
The snotites are, in fact, vast colonies of bacteria,
每天能长长1厘米
capable of going a centimetre a day.
在这个没有阳光的世界里
In this world without sunlight
这些细菌只能从硫化氢气体中吸收能量
these bacteria extract energy from the hydrogen sulphide gas.
像这样的细菌被称为嗜极生物
Bacteria like these are known as extremofile
因为它们能在这种极端环境中生存
because of their ability to survive in such extreme conditions.
这些嗜极生物还在这个洞中 扮演着另一个非常重要的角色
And these extremofiles play another important role in this cave.
令人吃惊的是  它们竟然是食物链中的第一环
Surprisingly, they are the basis of a food chain
用以养活其它生物  例如这些蚋的幼虫
which supports, amongst other creatures, the larvae of these midges.
露兹别墅山洞的生态系统的确非同寻常
Villa Luz's ecosystem was certainly very remarkable,
但是洞穴探险家们 很快又有了更惊人的发现
but cave explorers were soon to make an even more astonishing discovery.
谁能想到在这些贫瘠的土地下 有一处地下仙境
Beneath this arid landscape lies a subterranean wonderland.
没有水的地方似乎不可能有洞穴
Without water one might not expect to find any caves,
但是在美国这些荒凉起伏的山崖之下
but beneath these rolling desert slopes in the United States
存在着一座世界上最长、最深  也最令人惊奇的洞穴
lies one of the longest, deepest and most surprising caves in the world.
它的秘密直到1986年才被人们发现
Its secrets remained unknown until 1986,
洞穴专家们在松散的岩层中 挖出了一条几十米深的通道
when cavers dug through several metres of loose rock
直达这个深渊的底部
to the bottom of this pit.
他们把这个洞命名为“龙舌兰洞”
They named the cave 'Lechuguilla'
自从那次发现之后  迄今已测绘了120多英里的地道
and since this discovery more than 120 miles of passageways have been mapped.
第一批探险家进入这个洞后
When the first explorers descended,
没有一个人能预料到它竟然有这么大
no-one guessed at the sheer size of this cave.
即便如此 这也不能算是最大的惊奇
But even that was not going to be the biggest surprise.
不久他们便意识到龙舌兰洞很快就会
Little did they realise that Lechuguilla would soon
被全世界的洞穴专家公认为地球上最美丽的洞穴
be regarded by cavers the world over as the most beautiful of all caves.
因为他们发现了一些 地底世界中最精美的构造
They were about to discover some of the most exquisite formations ever seen underground.
石壁上布满了光洁美丽的脆弱结晶
The walls were covered with the most delicate and fragile crystals.
许多结晶都是由石膏组成
Many of these crystals were made of gypsum,
一种硫酸钙沉积而来的矿物
a mineral that comes from limestone.
它们绵延不绝
And there was mile after mile of them.
水是大部分洞穴的建造者
Water is the creator of most caves,
但是 和其它石灰岩溶洞不同的是
but, unlike all other limestone caves,
龙舌兰洞中的岩石并非被流水侵蚀
Lechuguilla's rock had not been eaten away by running rainwater.
而是因为其它的作用力
Something else was responsible.
龙舌兰洞中唯一的水 来自这些平静清澈的水塘
The only water Lechuguilla has are these wonderfully still clear pools.
随着探险家们深入洞穴
As the explorers went deeper into the cave,
他们发现了成片叹为观止的地貌
they came across whole galleries filled with the most unusual formations,
例如这些5米高的石锥  上面布满了雪霜一样的松脆结晶
like these 5-metre cones, frosted with the most delicate crystals.
龙舌兰洞的石膏结晶群
It was Lechuguilla's gypsum crystals
使科学家们产生了 这个巨洞如何形成的疑问
that made scientists question how these caverns were formed.
他们发现龙舌兰洞的石灰岩 实际上是被硫酸侵蚀的
They discovered that Lechuguilla's limestone had actually been eaten away by sulphuric acid,
凿穿了差不多数英里的石灰岩
cutting through literally miles of limestone.
硫酸在溶解石灰岩的同时
And when sulphuric acid dissolves limestone
也留下了石膏
it leaves behind gypsum,
它们最终形成了龙舌兰洞的奇景
the basis of Lechuguilla's remarkable formations.
这里有一组景观
And there was one set,
位于地表之下1英里多的地方
more than a mile from the surface,
美得简直无法令人相信
that almost defied belief.
“灯饰大厅”是最后被发现的厅洞
The Chandelier Ballroom was the ultimate discovery.
这里尽是6米多长的结晶群
With its six-metre long crystals
它可以说是世界上最奇异的厅洞
it's surely the most bizarre cave chamber in the world.
而石壁上还有更惊人的发现
And the walls had one further surprise.
嗜极细菌在岩壁上自我生长
Extremofile bacteria were found to be feeding on the rock itself.
生命彻底脱离太阳能量 却依然生存的现象
The discovery of life that exists without drawing any of its energy from the sun
再一次向我们展示了地底世界 是多么的复杂和惊人
shows us once again how complex and surprising the underground world can be.
每年 探险家们都会测绘 上百英里新的洞穴通道
Each year explorers chart over a hundred miles of new cave passages.
但世界上仍有一半石灰岩洞尚未被开发
But with half the world's limestone still to be explored,
谁知道还会有多少个龙舌兰洞 等着人们去发现呢
who knows how many Lechuguillas are still waiting to be discovered?